<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-04-13T11:50:50-07:00</updated><id>https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/feed.xml</id><title type="html">A Way to Wander</title><subtitle>An adventure blog for people on a budget.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Backpacking in the Sespe Wilderness</title><link href="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/backpacking/2019/04/08/backpacking-sespe-wilderness.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Backpacking in the Sespe Wilderness" /><published>2019-04-08T16:28:27-07:00</published><updated>2019-04-08T16:28:27-07:00</updated><id>https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/backpacking/2019/04/08/backpacking-sespe-wilderness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/backpacking/2019/04/08/backpacking-sespe-wilderness.html">&lt;p&gt;With a grunt, I pulled my pack up from the ground, leaning forward so the weight would fall squarely on my back as I pulled it around. Still facing the ground I clipped the waist strap and pulled, feeling it tighten and the weight settle on my hips as I stood. With a shiver, I looked around the familiar parking lot, that we had visited many times over the years. It was colder than it had ever been, it was our first time coming in the winter, and we were expecting bad weather. With one last look at the car, which too had been upgraded from our first trip, we set off along the familiar trail, that differed only in the glittering frost covering the plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all began around four years ago, I had just gotten my driver’s license so naturally, my friends and I packed up to go on our first parent-free backpacking trip. This was the first of many trips that we would take into the Sespe Wilderness. Our first trip was a three-day weekend in the spring, with four overpacked and nervous teenage girls. Even though it was spring, the temperatures soared and we found ourselves hating the seemingly never-ending series of ups and downs. On the trail, we only passed a few groups but did see a pack of boy scouts scurrying around in a little valley around halfway to Willett.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time we did this trip we didn’t even make it to Willett Campground and ended up settling at Oak Flat for the first night. The next day, we left our camp and continued on in the hopes of finding Willett’s hot tub for a quick day soak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplest way to find Willett Hot Tub is to follow the main trail and wait for a sharp right down a decently steep short incline to a very shallow and wide river crossing. After crossing the river one should continue along the trail for about 5 minutes and then turn left down a well traveled incline that splits off from the main trail. Here one must cross the river bed and continue straight towards the mountains. At the very base of the mountains there is a cabin and a group of shacks next to an open horse pasture. In front of these cabins you will find a trail running along the base of the mountains, following this trail will lead up the mountain to the Willett Hot Spring tub. In recent years, the trail up to the hot tub has become increasingly sketchy. At points the ground consists of a thin layer of slippery gravel, over hard packed dirt with a near sheer drop off on one side, and on the other side loose dirt with nothing to grip onto. (Keep in mind going down will be worse than going up) At the top of the hill there will be a small flat clearing, where people sometimes camp, right before a clump of trees and brush. To find the tub, one must go straight into the brush, and follow the water uphill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In future trips, we were able to make it to Willett in 1 day, roughly 14 miles, and were even lucky enough to stay in the cabin for a night. And yet we were never able to make it all the way to Sespe Hot Springs. We had always turned back too soon, once even stopping right before the last uphill before the trail division, giving up before seeing the old rusted sign pointing to Sespe. Regardless, this winter, more than four years after our first trip we finally made it all the way to Sespe Hot Springs. There we bathed in the warm stream under the starlight, exhausted but extremely pleased with ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned from all of our old mistakes and gave ourselves four days rather than the usual three to more comfortably travel the distance. The first night was the hardest, the entire night it rained while we huddled together in one of the old shacks at Willett listening to the rain hit the corrugated steel and the wind shake the structure late into the night. The next day the clouds cleared and we continued on to Sespe where we relaxed and melted off the fatigue from the miles logged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of four days, we left the wilderness relaxed, covered in the mud and ready to face the new year. Perhaps it was the fact we had failed so many times, or perhaps it was the company, the chance to reconnect with old high school friends, but overall we were left with feelings of excitement and energy that overshadowed the deep exhaustion of our muscles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-few-noteworthy-tidbits&quot;&gt;A few noteworthy tidbits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hiking in the summer is miserable, endless up and downs in the burning heat, and a constant desire to stop at any available water source and lay down in the shade. The winter faces its own issues, unpredictable weather and a constant cold. And yet, the winter is so much better, albeit more crowded, the warmth of Willett and Sespe gently pull you away from the cold and offer a reprieve that though it only lasts for less than an hour, feels longer than the time spent agonizing with every step. In addition, dogs are welcome on the trail, and many groups are accompanied with furry companions, some even with their own pack. On one occasion Raven, my black lab, joined us on an excursion and ended the trip with beat up paws, so if traveling with a dog I would suggest either going in the winter or buying your dog some shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;distances&quot;&gt;Distances&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Piedra Blanca Trailhead to Willett – 9.6 miles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Willett to Sespe Hot Springs – 5.6 miles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total One Way – 15.2 miles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Round Trip – 30.4 miles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-to-get-there&quot;&gt;How to get there&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m14!1m8!1m3!1d13235.522398050593!2d-118.4192231!3d33.9699083!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x80e9bc4975e6a3eb%3A0x35f7bf848306d349!2sPiedra+Blanca+Trailhead!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1554948377879!5m2!1sen!2sus&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;border:0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;necessary-permits&quot;&gt;Necessary Permits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adventure Pass (Can get at local sporting goods/hiking stores)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.preventwildfireca.org/Campfire-Permit/&quot;&gt;Campfire Permit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cost-estimate&quot;&gt;Cost Estimate&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$35.00 iodine, fuel, map&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$26.26 food&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$30.00 Adventure Pass&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;$30.42 per person&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;packing-list&quot;&gt;Packing List&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out our General Packing List for Backpackers&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="backpacking" /><category term="wilderness" /><category term="outdoor" /><summary type="html">With a grunt, I pulled my pack up from the ground, leaning forward so the weight would fall squarely on my back as I pulled it around. Still facing the ground I clipped the waist strap and pulled, feeling it tighten and the weight settle on my hips as I stood. With a shiver, I looked around the familiar parking lot, that we had visited many times over the years. It was colder than it had ever been, it was our first time coming in the winter, and we were expecting bad weather. With one last look at the car, which too had been upgraded from our first trip, we set off along the familiar trail, that differed only in the glittering frost covering the plants.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">General Packing List for Backpacking</title><link href="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/backpacking/2019/04/08/general-packing-list-backpacking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="General Packing List for Backpacking" /><published>2019-04-08T16:28:27-07:00</published><updated>2019-04-08T16:28:27-07:00</updated><id>https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/backpacking/2019/04/08/general-packing-list-backpacking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/backpacking/2019/04/08/general-packing-list-backpacking.html">&lt;p&gt;Be sure to check both the weather and all of your gear before each trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;group-gear&quot;&gt;Group Gear&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First aid (allergy, Advil, blister pads, band-aids, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emergency blanket(?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Water filter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iodine tablets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flashlights&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tent (size will depend on the number and size of the people on the trip)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tarp&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rope&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lighters and matches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stove&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fuel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pots &amp;amp; pans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small shovel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Toilet paper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;individual-gear--clothing&quot;&gt;Individual Gear &amp;amp; Clothing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleeping pad&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleeping bag&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Swiss army knife&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wind/rain jacket&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fleece jacket&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extra fleece jacket (or hoodie)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sweat pants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thermal Leggings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hiking pants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shorts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tops&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Underwear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multiple pairs of thick hiking socks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sleeping socks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Beanie&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mug&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fork &amp;amp; spoon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Toothpaste&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sunscreen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chapstick&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sun hat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sunglasses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small towel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contact lenses &amp;amp; solution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bathing suit (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plastic bag for wet swimsuit (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flip flops (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="backpacking" /><category term="wilderness" /><category term="outdoor" /><category term="gear" /><summary type="html">Be sure to check both the weather and all of your gear before each trip.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kyoto</title><link href="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/traveling/2019/04/08/kyoto-japan.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kyoto" /><published>2019-04-08T16:28:27-07:00</published><updated>2019-04-08T16:28:27-07:00</updated><id>https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/traveling/2019/04/08/kyoto-japan</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/traveling/2019/04/08/kyoto-japan.html">&lt;p&gt;Kyoto is a very touristy city filled with what seems like an endless supply of temples. The temples tend to blur together, with a single exception, Kokedera, a moss temple. While planning our trip this is one of the few places I insisted we go, I have always loved moss, and a temple cultivating the beauty of moss seemed like a dream world. So immediately after purchasing our plane tickets we sent in a reservation by mail to the temple, or rather Hirari did unbeknownst to Katie and me. (The request to visit the temple must be sent in advance and from an address in Japan).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get to the temple, we took a local bus line from Kyoto up a mountain road along an impressive river. Along the way we stopped at a shopping area, filled with all variety of Kyoto specials, in particular an abundance of yatsuhashi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, we took a much smaller bus across the river and up a narrow winding road, all the way to the final bus stop.We continued on foot until we reached a small stone bridge crossing a creek bed. Upon entering the gates, we were quickly herded with a group of other tourists through a mossless courtyard, to a small outdoor shelter connected to the temple. We removed our shoes, and headed into the temple, where the murmur of talk abruptly cut off as people respectfully silenced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were led into a room with rows of low tables, with two copies of the sutra sitting on top with an inkwell and a calligraphy brush. The interior of the temple was symmetrical with rows of low tables facing inwards into the empty space in the center of the room in front of a large alcove, from which an ornate statue looked out. Each table had a simple arrangement, a thin cushion to sit upon, and atop the table an inkwell and calligraphy brush with thick bristles. The items we would read to copy a portion of the sutra. Luckily, we had finer brushes we had brought. Hirari, always the forward thinker had made us buy some the day before, much to my objection of spending unnecessary money. So when we sat down seiza in front of the low desks, I wordlessly held out my hand to accept the thinner brush from Hirari. We immediately began are grueling tracing of an outlined sutra while sitting in seiza, while a buddhist monk chanted. I would like to say that I reached a deep meditative state as I wordlessly copied the kanjis, and became lost in the monk’s steady melodic chant. However, despite my best efforts I was unable to ignore my worldly pains, largely the discomfort in sitting seiza. Within, five minutes it was taking all of my willpower to maintain my position as I glared at the seemingly never ending columns of kanjis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon the monks began releasing people, wordlessly taking their papers and directing them to the gardens. Now, I’m not proud of this, but every time someone left the room with their unfinished sutra, I vehemently glared, annoyed that the monks had allowed them to leave with an uncompleted sutra. I was left in desperation, my legs ached and I wanted to be done. Slowly my kanji had become sloppier and sloppier, albeit slightly more natural and confident looking, as my pain had grown. Yet in retrospect, and a college psychology course later, I can’t help but wonder if perhaps that discomfort and pain made the experience what it was, a majestic world of moss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in the end, as most people would say, all the pain and discomfort leading up to the experience was completely worth it. We wandered through moss filled gardens, by ponds and lakes, across bridges traversing neatly lined streams of the clearest water. Up and around small mountain paths surrounded by comforting shades of green, all the while immersed in a fresh smelling world, as sprinkles of water brought our skin to life with little pricks. It was a world in of itself, becoming more detailed with every step, every pause we took was delighted with an unceasing source of detail. Too soon my body once again rebelled, this time with hunger, and we left the compound desperate for food. I was left with a feeling of distance, where the mind is somewhere up in the clouds tethered to the body by the thinnest of threads, the most tumultuous connection. Soon the rich smells of food, and the cold of the rain cemented the connection and the feelings faded.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="traveling" /><category term="asia" /><category term="japan" /><category term="kyoto" /><summary type="html">Kyoto is a very touristy city filled with what seems like an endless supply of temples. The temples tend to blur together, with a single exception, Kokedera, a moss temple. While planning our trip this is one of the few places I insisted we go, I have always loved moss, and a temple cultivating the beauty of moss seemed like a dream world. So immediately after purchasing our plane tickets we sent in a reservation by mail to the temple, or rather Hirari did unbeknownst to Katie and me. (The request to visit the temple must be sent in advance and from an address in Japan).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Northern Japan</title><link href="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/traveling/2019/04/08/northern-japan.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Northern Japan" /><published>2019-04-08T16:28:27-07:00</published><updated>2019-04-08T16:28:27-07:00</updated><id>https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/traveling/2019/04/08/northern-japan</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/traveling/2019/04/08/northern-japan.html">&lt;p&gt;After graduating high school my friends and I had one goal. One last adventure together before college. The only problem was overprotective parents and the daunting possibility of traveling throughout a country with no real “adult” help. (I quote adult, because now in college, my view of what it means to be an adult has completely changed) At this point in our lives, I think we almost needed to prove that we could function independently and survive in a foreign environment. So we shoved any misconceptions and worries we had about college out of our mind and spent the last half of our senior year planning our first trip together out of the country. After much debate, and some very good points on Hirari and Katie’s side, we settled on going to Japan, a quite different conclusion than the European backpacking trip I had in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given our inexperience we devoted an extreme amount of time to research and planning, some of which paid off and others parts seemed excessive. On the bright side our intensive planning, is very helpful in providing cost estimates and travel information for anyone interested in traveling throughout Japan. For this trip we decided to have a home base, rather than packing light, where we stayed in Hirari’s grandfathers house in Nagoya and took all of our multi-day trips from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We traveled to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kyoto&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mt. Fuji&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hokkaido&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kamakura&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nagoya&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tokyo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="traveling" /><category term="asia" /><category term="japan" /><category term="kyoto" /><summary type="html">After graduating high school my friends and I had one goal. One last adventure together before college. The only problem was overprotective parents and the daunting possibility of traveling throughout a country with no real “adult” help. (I quote adult, because now in college, my view of what it means to be an adult has completely changed) At this point in our lives, I think we almost needed to prove that we could function independently and survive in a foreign environment. So we shoved any misconceptions and worries we had about college out of our mind and spent the last half of our senior year planning our first trip together out of the country. After much debate, and some very good points on Hirari and Katie’s side, we settled on going to Japan, a quite different conclusion than the European backpacking trip I had in mind.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vasquez Rocks</title><link href="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/hiking/2019/04/08/vasquez-rocks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vasquez Rocks" /><published>2019-04-08T16:28:27-07:00</published><updated>2019-04-08T16:28:27-07:00</updated><id>https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/hiking/2019/04/08/vasquez-rocks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/hiking/2019/04/08/vasquez-rocks.html">&lt;p&gt;An ethereal landscape fitting of another planet Vasquez Rocks is only an hour outside of LA but seems like a different world. The rocks emerge from the ground at unnatural angles, like books leaning in a row, creating complex rock formations that are quite easy for anyone to ascend. It makes the perfect day trip out of LA, and is relatively empty, at least during winter. Katie and I visited Vasquez rocks just before Christmas immediately after a rainstorm and were able to witness dramatic clouds pushed around by chilling winds as we scrambled up the rocky terrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to other places with climbable rocks, Vasquez Rocks is not only easier to climb/hike, but are also finer grain, meaning that, worst case scenario, one can climb the most recognizable rock formation barefoot, as Katie did, which she highly recommends. Otherwise, it is a prudent idea to bring shoes with a good grip to aid in ascending steep inclines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great thing about Vasquez Rocks is it is accessible, even to the most budget conscious college students, as the park itself has no entry fee yet has similar facilities to that of a National Park. The visitors center’s walls are lined with maps and small glass enclosures with a small variety of local animals. Inside, park rangers are available for any questions or trail recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the wide variety of hiking trails, a portion of the PCT also runs through the park, providing the opportunity to walk just a tiny portion of the 2,650 mile trail. Of the hiking trails, there are trails for both pedestrians and equestrians. There is also the less expensive and legal option of participating in day horseback riding programs in the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unique landscape not only allows for a fun hiking experience, but also dramatic photographs (according to Katie, all of my photographs were subpar). This unique landscape has in turn made Vasquez rocks a prominent filming location where notable TV Shows and Movies, such as Star Trek and Austin Powers, have been filmed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="hiking" /><category term="outdoor" /><summary type="html">An ethereal landscape fitting of another planet Vasquez Rocks is only an hour outside of LA but seems like a different world. The rocks emerge from the ground at unnatural angles, like books leaning in a row, creating complex rock formations that are quite easy for anyone to ascend. It makes the perfect day trip out of LA, and is relatively empty, at least during winter. Katie and I visited Vasquez rocks just before Christmas immediately after a rainstorm and were able to witness dramatic clouds pushed around by chilling winds as we scrambled up the rocky terrain.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Whitney</title><link href="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/backpacking/2019/04/08/whitney.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Whitney" /><published>2019-04-08T16:28:27-07:00</published><updated>2019-04-08T16:28:27-07:00</updated><id>https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/backpacking/2019/04/08/whitney</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/backpacking/2019/04/08/whitney.html">&lt;p&gt;It was my first solo backpacking trip and I had high expectations. I was going to climb Mt. Whitney during a five-day trip through the High Sierras. It was the most mentally and physically difficult trip I have ever done. I planned to hike ~12 miles into Rock Creek through Cottonwood Pass on the first day, the next day ~7 miles to Guitar Lake, and on the third day I would summit Mt.Whitney and return to Guitar Lake. My last two days I would hike out to Rock Creek, and then all the way out of Cottonwood Pass. It was a fantastic plan. I still stand by it. It would have split the distances up perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was one small problem, elevation. The morning of September 22nd I woke up at 4am from my home in LA and drove three hours to the Eastern Interagency Center to get a five-day walk-in permit for Cottonwood Pass. By 9am I had the pass in hand and had already ascended ~9,000 ft on a narrow winding road to the base of the Cottonwood Pass Trail. By 11am I was at Chicken Spring Lake (~11,200 ft) refilling water. That was as far as I got. I tried to keep going, but all of a sudden I was hit by fatigue, every step left me out breath and my head swirling. Realizing I could go no further I painstakingly began setting up camp. Every step exhausted me as preparations stretched themselves over a couple of hours. Wearily I forced myself to eat a couple of bites before cuddling up in my sleeping bag to a fitful night of sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next morning I woke up tired but not light-headed. Where the night before a couple of steps would leave me out of breath, now I could walk at least 100 ft and only be panting slightly. I mention this for one crucial point, ALLOW TIME FOR ACCLIMATION. Some small little version of me was still determined to get to the top of Mt. Whitney, so with a small sigh I decided to hike to Crabtree from Chicken Spring, a distance of approximately ~15 miles. It was a hard day filled with constant elevation change, and barely any flat. On the way I ran into two rangers, one of which who asked for my full name, leaving me with a sick feeling that she surely thought I was going to die. (I realize this is just a safety thing, but at the time it scared me) I arrived just after dark at lower Crabtree and began plotting my Whitney ascent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the morning of the 24th at 8am I began the path to Whitney. People who say it is easy are either in phenomenal shape or are simply lying. Every step I took after Guitar Lake on those 11 switchbacks was hell. I had already spent hours walking up hill to simply get to that point and was quite done going up, but I still had ~2,500 ft of vertical elevation to gain. I honestly don’t know where I found the willpower to keep going. Every time I stopped to catch my breath I told myself it would be okay to just turn around, but some part of me kept pushing, it told me I didn’t have to quit. I knew no one, including myself, would be disappointed if I had to turn around, and yet I kept going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 3:30 pm I finally saw the hut at the top. I somehow found the energy to smile as I forced my feet through the final couple hundred feet. At the hut I dropped my bag and looked at the uninterrupted views from every side. The site is something that cannot be captured by photos, or at least not my photos. There is sort of a delirious excitement to being at the very top. I couldn’t help but smile to myself as I climbed on top of a rock and thought to myself that I am higher than every other person on land in the U.S. Going down, I flew, every step was easy as I smiled at my own accomplishments, even with my speed I arrived at my campsite after nightfall, again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, I slept in. When I woke I felt as though my body had been beaten with a bag of bricks and then dragged behind a truck. Slowly and with a heaping plateful of pain I packed up camp and made my way to Rock Creek. Up until this point I have not addressed what it is like being alone in the wilderness. For each person I am sure it is drastically different. For me, my perception of it varied vastly with the time of day. In the mornings I woke up peaceful and content, in awe of the beauty and sounds that surrounded me. Around sunset the loneliness and silence would always hit me for an hour or so, my mind would leap into overdrive analyzing all the things that could possibly go wrong. After my panic, I was always left with a feeling of acceptance, that I was simply adrift in the world and should not worry about my place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mention this for one reason only, an interaction between me and a marmot. Being alone affords you a closer interaction with nature. Almost everyday I would come within 10 feet of deer who would gaze at me with mild surprise, but without fear, who would simply continue munching on grass as though I wasn’t even there. On that fated day I was heading back to Rock Creek. I heard a loud screech and looked to my right to see a marmot sitting upon a rock staring at me. Intrigued, I walked closer and he quickly dashed away. With a sigh I was about to continue onwards when I saw him poke his head out of a hole five feet away from me. Thus began my conversation with the marmot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me: Why hello there marmot. How are you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marmot: &lt;em&gt;Sticks head out a little more&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me: I am well, a bit sore but what can you do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marmot: &lt;em&gt;Stares&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me: &lt;em&gt;Proceeds to take 20 photos&lt;/em&gt; Thank you for your time, I really appreciate you coming out like this. &lt;em&gt;Bows to Marmot, and takes a step away&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marmot: &lt;em&gt;Disappears down the marmot hole&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yeah, I had a conversation with a marmot. I regret nothing, it was fantastic, and wonderfully intimate. That is the benefit of backpacking alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-i-learned&quot;&gt;What I learned&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pack super light for climbing Whitney, if possible bring a light day pack to really shed the pounds. That does not mean skimping on water, bring lots of water&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acclimate or plan a super short day whenever you are planning to go above 10,000 ft of elevation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leave for Whitney really early in the day. Ideally leave from Guitar Lake if camping there is available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You don’t need a WAG bag while climbing up the backside!!!!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I lose my appetite at elevation, if you split up eating into bites over the course of the day you can still stomach foods. So unless you know how elevation affects you, don’t plan on having large meals that won’t travel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The road to the cottonwood pass trailhead is very windy and I would never want to drive it at night&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;distances&quot;&gt;Distances&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cottonwood Pass Trailhead to Chicken Spring – ~4 miles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chicken Spring to Lower Crab Tree – ~16 miles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lower Crab Tree to Whitney (x2 for the way back)- ~ 8 miles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lower Crab Tree to Rock Creek- ~8 miles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rock Creek to Cottonwood Pass Trailhead – ~12 miles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Round Trip – ~52 miles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;necessary-permits&quot;&gt;Necessary Permits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A standard wilderness backpacking permit from the Eastern Sierra Interagency Visitor Center&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;packing-list&quot;&gt;Packing List&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out our General Packing List for Backpacking&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="backpacking" /><category term="wilderness" /><category term="outdoor" /><summary type="html">It was my first solo backpacking trip and I had high expectations. I was going to climb Mt. Whitney during a five-day trip through the High Sierras. It was the most mentally and physically difficult trip I have ever done. I planned to hike ~12 miles into Rock Creek through Cottonwood Pass on the first day, the next day ~7 miles to Guitar Lake, and on the third day I would summit Mt.Whitney and return to Guitar Lake. My last two days I would hike out to Rock Creek, and then all the way out of Cottonwood Pass. It was a fantastic plan. I still stand by it. It would have split the distances up perfectly.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bouldering in Joshua Tree</title><link href="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/climbing/2019/04/08/bouldering-in-joshua-tree.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bouldering in Joshua Tree" /><published>2019-04-08T16:28:27-07:00</published><updated>2019-04-08T16:28:27-07:00</updated><id>https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/climbing/2019/04/08/bouldering-in-joshua-tree</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://krosengrant.github.io/wtw/climbing/2019/04/08/bouldering-in-joshua-tree.html">&lt;p&gt;This past weekend a group of friends and I decided to brave the government shut down and visit Joshua Tree. We weren’t sure what to expect and were prepared for crowds, trash, and camping on BLM (land outside of the park where camping is permitted). None of these stressors were encountered. Outside of campsites there were few people, the trash and toilets were well taken care of, and we were even lucky enough to stumble across an open campsite at Ryan Campground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent the weekend hiking to boulders and attempting to climb them. For all but one of us it was our first time climbing outside of a gym and it wasn’t at all what we expected. Despite the problems being of a much lower height we were intimidated by the rough texture of the rocks and the seemingly high consequences of falling against a substrate that felt like a cheese grater. Not only were the holds smaller but the footholds were often just little nubs or cracks along the rock surface. We had been majorly babied by the gyms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Halfway through the trip we learned that an outdoor V0 was equivalent to an indoor V3 or V4… Oops. With that in mind we began tackling sub V0’s to build up our confidence and by the end of the trip approached the V0’s with more knowledge and confidence. Though we were largely defeated by many routes we got a taste of outdoor climbing and will certainly be back for more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;guide-book-used&quot;&gt;Guide Book Used&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wolverinepublishing.com/store/joshua-tree-bouldering/&quot;&gt;Joshua Tree Bouldering - Robert Miramontes (2nd Edition)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;permits&quot;&gt;Permits&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None, because of the government shut down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;meal-plan&quot;&gt;Meal Plan&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These meals are designed to accommodate both vegetarians and vegans while minimizing cook/cleanup time to maximize climbing time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;day-1&quot;&gt;Day 1&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lunch -&lt;/strong&gt; Flatbread, hummus, carrots, cucumber, bell pepper, string cheese, salami&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dinner -&lt;/strong&gt; Hot dogs &amp;amp; veggie dogs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;day-2&quot;&gt;Day 2&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breakfast -&lt;/strong&gt; Oatmeal, apples, bananas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lunch -&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tasteofhome.com/recipes/black-bean-corn-quinoa/&quot;&gt;Quinoa salad&lt;/a&gt;, string cheese, salami, fruit, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dinner -&lt;/strong&gt; Gnocchi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;day-3&quot;&gt;Day 3&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breakfast -&lt;/strong&gt; Oatmeal, apples, bananas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lunch -&lt;/strong&gt; Flatbread, hummus, carrots, cucumber, bell pepper, string cheese, salami&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="bouldering" /><category term="climbing" /><category term="outdoor" /><summary type="html">This past weekend a group of friends and I decided to brave the government shut down and visit Joshua Tree. We weren’t sure what to expect and were prepared for crowds, trash, and camping on BLM (land outside of the park where camping is permitted). None of these stressors were encountered. Outside of campsites there were few people, the trash and toilets were well taken care of, and we were even lucky enough to stumble across an open campsite at Ryan Campground.</summary></entry></feed>